Finding Aid for Clyde H. Coombs Papers 1932-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Clyde H. Coombs Papers 1932-1988, 1964-1987
Coombs, Clyde Hamilton, 1912-
7 linear feet
Founder of the mathematical psychology program at the University of Michigan; correspondence, lectures, student notebooks, teaching files, and writing and research material.
90144 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Materials donated in 1989 by Lolagene C. Coombs, wife of Clyde H. Coombs (Donor No. 7709 ).
The collection is open for research.
Clyde H. Coombs, the founder of the Mathematical Psychology program at the University of Michigan, was born on July 22, 1912. He began his undergraduate work in engineering and mathematics at Santa Barbara State College, but changed his major to psychology and transferred to the University of California-Berkeley. He received his A.B. (1935) and M.S. (1937) from Berkeley, studying with Robert Tryon, Werner Brown, and Nathan Shock. Coombs then studied with and served as a research assistant to L. L. Thurstone at the University of Chicago. He received his Ph.D. from Chicago in 1940. During World War II, Coombs joined the U.S. War Department, serving in the Adjutant General's Office (AGO) in Washington, D.C. His work on the diagnosis and counseling of demobilized soldiers won him the Legion of Merit in 1945.
After the war, Coombs continued to work with the AGO, rising to the rank of major. Preferring a research life, Coombs returned to an academic setting in 1947 at the fast-growing Psychology Department at the University of Michigan. This was the beginning of a professional appointment which would continue beyond his nominal "retirement" in 1983. Coombs' superb abilities as a teacher, enormous productivity as a researcher and scholar, and his administrative capabilities served him well as he advanced to the rank of associate professor in 1949, full professor in 1953, and professor emeritus of psychology upon his retirement. Throughout his long career at the University of Michigan, Coombs travelled widely, lectured, and was a visiting scholar at several schools.
It was during his first such academic leave at Harvard University in 1948-1949 that Coombs began to bring together his interests in mathematics and psychology in the measurement of subjective phenomena. He concluded that psychological measurements could be thought of in terms of two spatial relationships, dominance and proximity, and set theory. He also noted that psychologists chose their model of measurement based on their subjective theoretical ideas rather than holding that measurements were objective data. These ideas on the dynamics of data, measurement, and subjectivity dominated Coombs' research and teaching during the 1950s as he produced several articles and designed seminars to further the research. In this he epitomized the researcher as teacher. Coombs so quickly incorporated the results of his experiments into his teaching that the texts for the courses consisted of mimeographs of his latest work and thought. Eventually Coombs pulled these ideas together in his seminal work A Theory of Data (1964), completed after a year's fellowship at the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences in Palo Alto.
Coombs' work with mathematics, measurement, and psychology was rewarded with the founding of the Michigan Mathematical Psychology Program in the early 1960s. This institution provided a framework in which Coombs could do his research and continue to attract graduate students interested in understanding human behavior quantitatively. During this time Coombs developed two concepts on preference and decision making, "unfolding theory" and "portfolio theory" which were closely linked to his earlier idea that measurement could be reduced to orders or proximities. In addition to his usual load of teaching, research and writing, and administration, Coombs collaborated with former students Amos Tversky and Robyn Dawes on Mathematical Psychology (1970). This work was enthusiastically reviewed and soon came to be the standard text in the field.
Coombs remained very productive throughout his career, publishing over seventy-five articles and four books. His last book The Structure of Conflict (1988), was published shortly after Coombs' death in February 1988. This book was also a collaborative effort with a former student, George Avrunin. They examined the preference decisions made by two people seeking dissimilar outcomes and noted these decisions mirror behavior of a single person faced with one multivariate alternative. Throughout his career Coombs remained open to new ideas and was quick to lend his experience and expertise to his many students in collaborative efforts to get their work published. These students were appreciative of Coombs' efforts and formed a world-wide network of loyal friends.
Beyond his teaching and research, Coombs served his science and profession tirelessly. His offices and roles included: president of the Society for Mathematical Psychology (1977), president of the Psychometric Society (1955-1956), president of the Division of Measurement and Evaluation of the American Psychological Association (1958-1959), membership on a wide variety of editorial boards, and on many research review committees for the National Science Foundation. His professional honors included being: an honorary fellow of the American Statistical Society (1959), a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences (1977), elected to the National Academy of Sciences (1982), a Fulbright (1955-1956) and a Guggenheim fellow (1970), and awarded the Distinguished Scientific Contribution Award by the APA in 1985.
Coombs met his future wife, Lolagene Convis, while both were graduate students at the University of Chicago. They were married and had two sons, Steve and Doug. They shared an interest in travel and co-authored articles on family composition preferences in the 1970s.
The Clyde H. Coombs papers document the teaching and research aspects of the career of America's foremost mathematical psychologist. In many ways the collection reflects the close congruence between the teaching and research interests of Coombs. His research ideas permeated his teaching; what he learned while teaching came to be incorporated into his research. If Coombs embodied the model teacher-researcher, the collection only palely reflects this ideal in all save his theory of data research and seminars. This is largely because of a 1974 fire at the Coombs' home which destroyed all the materials he had stored there. Thus the collection, while strong in parts, has significant lacunae, including all documentation of Coombs' work as an editor, his work for the American Psychological Association, and, most importantly, his drafts of Mathematical Psychology. The strength of the collection is its thorough coverage of Coombs' teaching during the 1950s when his seminars and mimeographs of summary lectures justly earned a reputation as groundbreaking work among psychologists. The collection's detailed documentation of Coombs' later research on mathematical psychology will also be of interest to the specialist.
The Coombs papers span the years 1932-1988 and are organized into six series: Vitae and Biographies, Correspondence, Lectures, Student Notebooks, Teaching, and Writing and Research. The first three series reflect Coombs' arrangement scheme and remain in original order. Given the thin line between teaching and research for Coombs, the latter two series might well be viewed as complementary units. The material in these two series was rearranged in the course of processing to bring it into a rough chronological order with similar material (courses or research projects) placed together. In addition to these five series, there is one folder of biographical material in the front of Box 1.
Subjects:
Coombs, Clyde H. (Clyde Hamilton), 1912-1988; Psychology--Mathematical models.; Psychometrics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Mathematical Psychology Program.
Contributors:
Coombs, Lolagene C.
- Vitae and Biographies 1981-1988
  - Documents containing information about Coombs (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1963-1988
  The Correspondence (1963-1988) series runs one linear foot and is arranged chronologically, consisting of an annual folder of correspondence for every year except 1975. This correspondence is primarily professional in nature dealing with recommendations of individuals, descriptions of ongoing research and ideas for publication, and arrangements for seminars, colloquia, and meetings. Given his propensity for travel and his stature in the field, it is not surprising that Coombs had a world-wide network of correspondents significant in psychology.
  - 1963-1988, 25 folders (Box 1)
    missing 1975 correspondence
- Lectures 1958-1988
  The Lectures (1958-1988) series was labelled "trip files" by Coombs since it primarily dealt with lectures, symposia, and courses offered off of the University of Michigan campus. The few lectures given at the University of Michigan were presented outside Coombs' normal classroom setting. This series comprises just over one linear foot of materials and primarily consists of lecture notes and correspondence related to Coombs' latest research. Since Coombs was usually addressing a well-informed audience of his peers or graduate students, these materials detail the development of his thinking on theory of data, portfolio theory, unfolding technique, risk and decision making, family composition preference, and single peaked preference in the structure of conflict.
  - Various venues, "Decision Making," 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - European lecture notes, Spring 1964 (Box 2)
  - Wayne State University, "Portfolio Theory of Decision Making," April 1966 (Box 2)
  - Netherlands University Foundation for International Cooperation (summer course) 1966 (Box 2)
  - Purdue University, "Scaling Theory and Data Theory," December 1966 (Box 2)
  - University of Wisconsin, "Portfolio Decision Theory," March 1967 (Box 2)
  - Aix-en-Provence (summer course), "Portfolio Theory," 1967 (Box 2)
  - Political Science Consortium, "Conjoint Measurement," July 1967 (Box 2)
  - University of Southern California site visit January 1968 (Box 2)
  - University of Pennsylvania, "Theory of Data," February 1968 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Mathematical Psychology, "Measurement of Risk," March 1968 (Box 2)
  - Stanford University, "Measurement and Risk," August 1968 (Box 2)
  - University of California-San Diego (winter course) 1969 (Box 2)
  - London International Congress, "Conjoint Measurement," August 1969 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University Mathematical Psychology, "Portfolio Theory/Risk Theory," April 1970 (Box 2)
  - University of Minnesota, Symposium on Modern Methods of Measurement May 1970 (Box 2)
  - Australia (sabbatical courses) 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Georgia Tech, "Mathematical Psychology of Risk," June 1973 (Box 2)
  - Northern Illinois University, "Portfolio Theory," Fall 1974 (Box 2)
  - University of Pennsylvania, "Unidimensional Unfolding: Single Peakedness," October 1974 (Box 2)
  - Leiden, "Measurement and Analysis of Family Composition," May 1975 (Box 2)
  - Honolulu East-West Center, "Family Composition Preference Models," June 1975 (Box 2)
  - University of Pennsylvania, "Seriousness of Crime Survey," October 1975 (Box 2)
  - Washington, D.C., Decision Making Workshop September 1976 (Box 2)
  - Germany, "Multidimensional Analysis of Similarity," December 1976 (Box 2)
  - Washington, D.C., "Fair Evaluation of Research Proposals," February 1977 (Box 2)
  - Washington, D.C., "Analysis of Case Report Ratings," April 1977 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan, "Risk and Risky Decisions," May 1977 (Box 2)
  - American Psychological Association (Chicago), "Empirical Regularities and Theoretical Laws," September 1977 (Box 2)
  - Europe (sabbatical), "The 'Don't Know' Response," Winter 1978 (Box 2)
  - Various venues, "Joint Preference and the Logic of Conflict," 1975-1979 (Box 2)
  - U.S./U.S.S.R. Symposium, "Descriptive/Normative Models of Decision Making," Spring 1979 (Box 2)
  - Netherlands, "Chemoreception and Preference," May 1979 (Box 2)
  - Aachen, "Multidimensional Scaling," Spring 1980 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan March 1981
    - "Preference and Trade-offs" (Box 2)
    - "Conflict and Design" (Box 2)
    - "Family Composition Preference" (Box 2)
  - Dartmouth, "Empirical Study of the Election System," October 1982 (Box 2)
  - Hamburg, "Structure of Conflict/Single Peaked Functions," Spring 1983 (Box 2)
  - Calgary University, "Structure of Conflict," Fall 1984 (Box 2)
  - London School of Economics, "Structure of Conflict," 1985 (Box 2)
  - University of California-Santa Barbara, "From Preferential Theory to Structure of Conflict," Winter 1986 (Box 2)
  - American Psychological Association, "Preference Theory to Structure of Conflict," September 1986 (Box 3)
  - National Research Council, "Distributive Decision Making," October 1986 (Box 3)
  - National Research Council, "Isolation Research," January 1988 (Box 3)
- Student Notebooks 1932-1951
  The Student Notebooks (1932-1951) series comprises less than six linear inches of material and consists of notes taken by Coombs while he was a student at Berkeley and Chicago. It is interesting to note that Coombs continued to view himself as a student in some areas even after he was hired by the University of Michigan; his algebra and statistics notebooks bear witness to this refreshing humility.
  - Abstracts 1932-1940, 2 volumes; 1 folders (Box 3)
  - Probability and least squares 1938 (Box 3)
  - Psychophysics 1938 (Box 3)
  - Infinite series and definite integrals 1939 (Box 3)
  - Algebra (Berkhoff/McLane) 1948-1949 (Box 3)
  - Algebra (Thrall) 1949-1951 (Box 3)
  - Statistics circa 1949-1950 (Box 3)
- Teaching 1950-1988
  The material of the Teaching (1950-1988) series runs to nearly two linear feet and includes lecture notes, mimeographed handouts, lab assignments, bibliographies, tests, and summaries of students' preliminary exams. As previously noted these materials are in rough chronological order according to course. The researcher should note that course titles and numbering schemes change over time (i.e. the Theory of Data course was labelled Psychology 246 in the 1950s and Psychology 725 in the 1970s) and that similar material was covered in various courses. As noted above the real strength of this series lies in the mimeos of lecture summaries for the 1950s courses. These include notes from eminent University of Michigan teachers: Copi, Angell, Thrall, and Boulding, as well as guest lecturers: George Miller, R.D. Luce, and Louis Guttman. The Theory of Data materials from the 1960s and 1970s clearly show Coombs' commitment to teaching as he continued to revise his lecture notes even after writing the book on the subject.
  - Application of Mathematics to Social Science Seminar 1950-1959, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Theory of Psychological Measurement Seminar 1950-1952, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Theory of Measurement (Psychology 241) 1950-1953, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Theory of Data (Psychology 246) lab materials 1954-1959, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Mathematical Models/Decision Making (Psychology 521) 1952-1963, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Measurement Prelims (summaries) 1953-1963 (Box 4)
  - Mathematical Psychology (Psychology 201/621) 1959-1965 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Mathematical Psychology Program Summer Institute 1965-1967, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Mathematical Psychology Seminar (Psychology 721) 1958-1981
    - Additive Conjoint Measurement 1969-1981 (Box 4)
    - Family Composition Preferences 1972-1980 (Box 4)
    - Information Theory 1963-1972 (Box 4)
    - Mathematical Learning Theory 1966-1972 (Box 4)
    - Measurement Theory 1965-1979 (Box 4)
    - Polynomial Conjoint Measurement 1975-1979 (Box 4)
    - Risk Theory 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - Signal Detectability 1958-1972 (Box 4)
  - Theory of Data (Psychology 725) 1962-1988, 4 folders (Box 5)
- Writing and Research 1949-1988
  The Writing and Research (1949-1988) series runs to over two linear feet and includes materials ranging from raw data, to preliminary evaluations of data, to rough drafts of manuscripts, to reprints of published articles. The materials are arranged in a rough chronological order with ongoing research on one project grouped together. Although Coombs' work on The Theory of Data is well documented, most of his early research is not well covered. These materials may have been destroyed in the 1974 fire at Coombs' house since The Theory of Data was preserved in his office files. In general, the work after 1974 is more thoroughly documented than is the previous research. This series sheds light on Coombs research techniques and his close collaboration with other researchers.
  - Psychological Theory of Discrimination and Traits 1949 (Box 5)
  - The Scale Grid: Some Interpretations of Data Models 1949-1956 (Box 5)
  - Research ideas 1949-1964 (Box 5)
  - Theory of Data (draft essay) 1959 (Box 5)
  - Theory of Data (draft) 1960-1961
    - Part 1: Overview (Box 5)
    - Part 2: Preferential Choice Data (Box 5)
    - Part 3: Single Stimulus Data (Box 5)
    - Part 4: Stimulus Comparison Data (Box 5)
    - Part 5: Similarities Data (Box 5)
    - Part 6: Interrelations (Box 5)
  - Theory of Data (notes) 1951-1972
    - Quadrant I 1953-1960 (Box 5)
    - Quadrant II 1951-1961 (Box 5)
    - Quadrant III 1955-1960 (Box 5)
    - Quadrant IV 1955-1961 (Box 5)
    - Interquadrant relations 1958-1960 (Box 5)
    - Part 2: Preferential Choice Data 1958 (Box 5)
    - Part 3: Single Stimulus Data 1969 (Box 5)
    - Part 5: Similarities Data 1965-1972 (Box 5)
    - Part 6: Interrelations 1963-1968 (Box 5)
  - Expected Utility v. Portfolio Theory (with Lily Huang) 1970-1974 (Box 6)
  - Expanded Portfolio Theory (notes) 1975-1977 (Box 6)
  - Unfolding Theory (notes) 1973-1975 (Box 6)
  - What is Mathematical Psychology? 1974 (Box 6)
  - "Don't Know" Response 1975 (Box 6)
  - Research ideas 1973-1976 (Box 6)
  - Family Composition Planning (with Lolagene Coombs and Gary McClelland) 1973-1975 (Box 6)
  - Family Composition Planning (data) 1975 (Box 6)
  - Birth Order Effects (notes) 1975 (Box 6)
  - Stochastic Cumulative Scales (with Lolagene Coombs) 1975-1977 (Box 6)
  - Multiattribute One-Dimensional Perceived Risk (with Michael Donnell) 1975-1976 (Box 6)
  - Risk Preference in Lotteries (with Michael Donnell and Dick Kirk) 1976-1977 (Box 6)
  - Approach/Avoidance Theory of Preference (early Single Peaked Function work with George Avrunin) 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Single Peaked Preference Function (with George Avrunin) 1975-1977 (Box 6)
  - Single Peaked Function and Theory of Preference (notes, with George Avrunin) 1975-1980 (Box 6)
  - Goodness of Fit (with Bill Goldstein) 1977-1980 (Box 6)
  - Some Models of Preference for Choice Behavior 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - Conjoint Analysis of Bilinear Model of Risk (with Paul Lehner) 1977-1981, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Empirical Studies of Social Change: Elections (with Cohen and Chamberlain) 1979-1984 (Box 7)
  - Bilinear Experimental Design 1980 (Box 7)
  - Angus Campbell biographical memoirs 1987 (Box 7)
  - The Structure of Conflict 1987 (Box 7)
  - The Structure of Conflict (draft) 1987
    - Part 1: Type I Conflict (Box 7)
    - Part 2: Type II Conflict (Box 7)
    - Part 3: Type III Conflict (Box 7)
  - The Structure of Conflict (correspondence and notes) 1975-1988
    - Correspondence with George Avrunin 1983-1988, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Notes 1975-1987, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Reference notes 1980-1988, 2 folders (Box 7)